Kane Baccigalupi

935 Scenic Place Pleasant Hill, CA 94523 Mobile: 510-228-9669

Skill Summary:

Expert technical advisor with over 10 years experience as a CTO and expert consultant. Team leader dedicated to advancing and developing team members. Champion for organizational diversity and its benefits to business objectives. Business strategist focused on using technical innovation to move organizations quickly towards their objectives. Mentor, writer and speaker. Data driven decision maker focused on user research and customer validation. Public servant dedicated to bringing the best innovations from the private sector into government.

Experience:

Innovation Strategist, 18F, GSA

September 2015 - present

GSA's 18F is an IT innovation agency for the federal government. Worked on the strategy team, offering technical advice and hands-on support for moving agencies and their projects to better practices and outcomes.

Legacy Modernization, Lead:

Educated 18F leadership and staff about common patterns for legacy modernization. Crafted plans for Alaska and Missouri Medicaid related modernizations, starting with deep technical dive with 18F team members, a three-month prototyping vendor contract and concluding in modular procurement plan. Rebuilt technical and product strategy for Health and Human Services, Unaccompanied Children Program software modernization effor, switching from database encapsulation to transformation.

US Census Bureau, Engagement Lead:

Acted as a bridge between engineering teams and Census top leadership, introducing product development processes and improving agile practices for the 2020 internet data collection application. Lead discovery, improved software design practices, crafted a two day engineering design workshop. Worked with CIO and Deputy Director to address the highest risk issues for the decennial survey: cloud infrastructure and IT governance.

Environmental Protection Agency, E-Enterprise Program, Engineering Strategist:

Co-lead discovery for Combined Air Emissions Reporting. Crafted a data architecture that would allow state and federal program managers to understand the data reporting and query it for their own separate needs. Taught a two day agile workshop that bridged the gap between state and

EPA needs. Guided EPA towards low-risk, high-return solutions that could be completed within a month and establish trust with state participants.

Lead Agile Consultant, Ministry of Velocity

December 2014 - August 2015

Worked on engagements lasting from one day to six months, advising company leadership on building or rebuilding both their IT organization and their core software products.

Lead a one-day working session with engineering leadership at an enterprise SaaS company to tackle system instability, leading to data architecture solution that increased uptime. Provided expert technical and organizational advice to CEO/Founder of food delivery startup that was transitioning from a hastily built prototype to a scalable, customizable solution. Performed hands-on engineering and mentoring for two enterprise SaaS companies struggling with legacy code issues. Improved agile software practices, increased velocity, and re-architected failing systems and applications.

Acting Director, gSchool, Galvanize Inc.

August 2014 - November 2014

Increased operational efficiency of the web education school, while the company acquired the Zipfian academy and merged with the new University of New Haven backed masters program in data science. Oversaw instructions, admissions and student outcomes during the transition.

Reduced instructor costs by 30% and increased facility utilization at Boulder campus via concurrent classes. Launched San Francisco instruction campus, creating curriculum and leading instruction at the first web development six month course. Reorganized school-wide roles to increase efficiency, and improve instructor retention. Streamlined admissions from scattered ad hoc processes into a comprehensive system tracking leads to conclusion. Built a system of soft and hard metrics for estimating student success, removing bias from the admissions process and increasing diversity.

Chief Technical Officer, SocialChorus Inc.

November 2012 - July 2014

Transformed a brittle, monolithic legacy application into a high-performance, service-oriented architecture. Converted low-velocity, high-attrition engineering culture into a happy productive work environment. Crafted the product that became company's top competitive advantage via better user-interviews, user-testing and great agile practices.

Product:

Crafted the user-focused, real-time advocate experience that became the top competitive advantage for the company. Designed product via user interviews, rapid build-out of a working prototype, and finally an on-time, 6-week, agile execution plan. Enhanced agile process via stricter story processes, company-wide retrospectives and user-focused practices.

Engineering:

Transformed a stagnating, legacy application into a robust service-oriented architecture driving both scale and development speed. Separated administrative facing application from advocate facing application. Crafted high-performance services for tracking click traffic of promoted advocate content. Authored over 6 open source libraries including a mobile first front-end framework, and a framework for developing and deploying services.

Team Building:

Replaced existing small engineering team with a new group of ten dedicated developers, a Director of Engineering and QA staff. Rebuilt the product team. Created a successful internship program with graduates who converted to team leads. Improved engineering and company culture with a focus on problem solving and striving for practical best practices.

Senior Agile Consultant, Blazing Cloud

November 2011 - November 2012

Advised several companies about refining and improving development and agile practices to increase velocity. Blazing Cloud was acquired by Indiegogo in 2013.

Recruited and interviewed developer talent from intern to senior level with talents in Ruby, Javascript and Objective-C. Mentored interns, built internal company best practices, and advised on internal business and product decisions. Lead technical direction and product management on graphically intense mobile first application in HTML and Javascript.

Architect, Cohuman Inc.

October 2009 - August 2011

Second employee at SaaS company that was acquired acquired by MindJet and is currently offered as MindJet Connect as their task management solution. Planned and developed scalable features for a project management application with complex permissions and notifications systems. Designed an OAuth authenticated API.

Chief Technical Officer, Clerkdogs, Inc.

February 2009 - October 2009

Worked with CEO to build a combination of flexible options for movie recommendations: turn-key, whitelist solutions; data consumption via API and export. Data was acquired by Netflix in early 2010.

Transformed rough, untested prototype into two user facing applications: one for admin and one for consumers. Consumer application was a modular, composable application that could be graphically skinned to match company look and feel, and could be customized with components according to needs and costs. Hired and managed remote team. Pioneered agile practices and testing to increase velocity and stability.

Lead Developer, Integral Impressions

May 2008 - January 2009

Crafted a content management system sufficiently flexible that the company could rapidly build informational client websites, allowing the customer to add pages and customize content. Managed and hired remote contract team of engineers and infrastructure architects. Built and supervised handcrafted custom infrastructure and deployment scripts for web solutions. Lead engineering on larger custom web solutions with highly customized product and engineering needs.

Founder & Chief Technical Officer, GPC, Inc.

May 2005 - January 2008

Managed all aspects of the business: hiring contract labor, generating documentary content, getting press in national publications and developing software. Created web application solution for showcasing documentary video content in a variety of formats and sizes with the flexibility to adjust rapidly for best product market fit. Built a service oriented suite of custom database applications for scheduling and managing contract video production staff and interviewees. Scaled infrastructure to allow thousands of simultaneous streaming connections for special events. Crafted security architecture capable of storing important employment personally identifiable information.

Engineering Intern, CERN ATLAS Project, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory January 2002 - May 2005

Junior member of five person mechanical engineering team responsible for prototyping and building the inner and second layer of the ATLAS detector at CERN's Large Hadron Collider. Rebuilt microscope calibration algorithms to fix manufacturing problems with radial sensors. Created custom database application for analyzing radiation length and interference of detector on readings. Devised heat transfer and static force analysis simulation to validate models. Created CAD designs for insertion system for central detector and machined several components.

Database Consultant & Visual Designer, Self-employed

1995 - 2008

Worked with a variety of customers to solve software and/or product problems related to their business objectives. Created custom database applications from internal business processes in order to free up labor for higher level business concerns. Converted custom database applications to web solutions to increase availability, with an eye towards portability across infrastructure and data security. Generated product specification, easy to use user interfaces and visual design as needed.

Selected Speaking Engagements:

What the C? - Women Who Code. San Francisco 2015

Technical presentation on data structure that C programmers use to make the static language behave dynamically.

Long Live the Rubyist - Women Who Code, San Francisco 2015

Talk about concurrency limits in the Ruby programming language.

Going Evergreen - RubyConf 2014

Presentation on engineering and culture principles to avoid technical debt and create enjoyable, ongoing software work.

Diversity: Why? What? How? - Pivotal Labs 2014

Talk that describes the benefits and techniques for increasing engineering and product team diversity.

Coding Towards Diversity - O'Reilly Fluent Conference, 2013

Talk that takes a programmatic approach to solving the diversity problem in the tech industry.

Agua: A cool, clean drink of Ruby object persistence - RubyConf 2009

Proof of concept talk about creating a transparent persistence layer for pure Ruby objects.

Selected Technical Writing:

Choose Design over Architecture - 18F Blog

https://18f.gsa.gov/2015/11/17/choose-design-over-architecture

On inverting the architectural emphasis. Voted to front page of Hacker News and one of most popular post on 18F blog in 2015.

The Code is Just the Symptom - Personal Blog

https://medium.com/@rubyghetto/the-code-is-just-the-symptom-c77f43b29320

On two different companies and how leadership and Conway's law lead to the problems seen deep down in their code. Over 60,000 views. Voted to front page of Hacker News.

Education:

University of California, Berkeley, California - 2002 - 2004 *Advanced technical coursework for BS in Mechanical Engineering*

UC Berkeley Extension, San Francisco, California - 1998 - 1999 *Professional coursework on software and database design*

San Francisco Art Institute, San Francisco, California - 1993 BFA, Painting

Volunteer Work:

Board of Directors, Industry & Technical Advisor, Women Who Code, Inc. December 2013 - June 2015